<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Development | Because yes]]></title>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.com/blog/categories/development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-16T16:00:23+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mmoreram.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marc Morera]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[yuhu@mmoreram.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PDD, Pragmatic Driven Development, English version]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.com/blog/2014/10/26/pdd-pragmatic-driven-development-english/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-26T19:51:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.com/blog/2014/10/26/pdd-pragmatic-driven-development-english</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is just a translation of one of my previous posts, written in Spanish,
for Spaniard people. I just wanted to translate it and to propose my idea to the
entirely world, even knowing not everyone will be agree with my point of view.</p>

<p>You will find the original one <a href="http://mmoreram.com/blog/2014/10/06/pdd/">here</a></p>

<p>There is a trend, in my opinion, extremely annoying about how we should work in
any technical project. We have gone from being a voiceless sector to, for a
while, a small egomaniac movement with categorical thoughts, making some
monothematic readings so boring for the reader, just because these topics
iterated for the umpteenth time with a very theoretical speech, non practical at
all, far from the real life.</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s what we all need, a great doses of reality. Because reality is
practical, not logical.</p>

<p>From my point of view, and given my small experience, I think this movement has
to be eradicated to make way for a new movement of thought, maybe
circumstantially called PDD, Pragmatic Driven Development (You know&hellip; I can
also be so witty assigning new names and adding some cool tags to my Linkedin
profile&hellip;). And the truth is that I am so tired seeing that some people is
still telling me how I should do my job, what practices should I follow to make
it &ldquo;the right way&rdquo; and what guidelines I should take to not being far from the
real truth.</p>

<p>The real truth does not exist, or at least should not. Every single speech
should have an objective part, based in good practices, but also should have a
subjective part, relative to the real circumstances and taking care about the
needs of the project. So, this is not seemed to be understood by some people.
Seems that, like an outdated political movement, The ego blinds some people to
understand so much certainty (must be that we are too used to being treated like
sheeps&hellip; BeEeEe BeEeEe).</p>

<p>This is why I refuse to listen to such modernistic stupidity without solid
arguments. I refuse to be near this hype, created from this people that don&rsquo;t
have any other way to stand out than selling their unique thought like it was
the entrance of the heaven of wisdom. We have reached an illness point.</p>

<p>I personally always demand my attendees, or just the people that talk with me,
to have an owning point of view, to treat my single one just like another point
of view, even if they feel it is not correct, it is different or even distant
from theirs, and to use it as a starting point of constructive discussion.</p>

<p>Important, I&rsquo;m not telling that I disagree all these techniques, I&rsquo;m not telling
that all this architectural knowledge is not useful, I&rsquo;m not telling that
applying a great methodology is useless&hellip; I strongly think that all of them,
born inside great minds and actually tested with great results, are very useful
and really makes us better as developers, giving us more resources to work and
making us better able to do our job successfully. I have to tell also that since
I am actually practicing lot of them in my projects, like TDD, BDD and DDD, I
feel better and more comfortable. I say thanks for that! What I am actually
saying is that we are developers, not this kind of stupid people without
capacity analysis. At the moment we lose this capacity, we lose our value.</p>

<ul>
<li>Hey, dude! I am actually working on that project! Do you like it?</li>
<li>Well, I expect you are doing Hexagonal Architecture&hellip;</li>
<li>Hmmm&hellip; I don&rsquo;t really need it&hellip;</li>
<li>You don&rsquo;t need it? Sure you do!</li>
<li>In fact, not.</li>
<li>You are wrong!</li>
<li>Ok.</li>
</ul>


<p>It is all about thinking things, and make sure about what we really need at each
point, just ignoring everyone telling you, categorically, the way you need to do
your job.</p>

<p>I truly hope all this pantomime to be ended soon. I hope as well that one day we
will be able to work all together as a community or a team, this is what we
really need, keeping in mind what really matters: learning, teaching and doing
great projects, no matter the framework, the language even the architecture.</p>

<p>Have a really nice week, and enjoy your work :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PDD, Pragmatic Driven Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.com/blog/2014/10/06/pdd/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.com/blog/2014/10/06/pdd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hay una tendencia, a mi parecer, extremadamente molesta sobre como se tiene que
trabajar en cualquier proyecto técnico. Hemos pasado de ser un sector con poca
voz, a ser, desde hace un tiempo, un pequeño movimiento ególatra de pensamientos
categóricos que hacen que según qué lecturas monotemáticas aburran al lector con
tópicos iterados por enésima vez y con un discurso teórico, nada práctico, muy
lejos de la realidad.</p>

<p>Y esto es lo que necesitamos, una buena dosis de realidad. Porque la realidad es
práctica, no teórica.</p>

<p>Desde mi punto de vista, y según la lectura que puedo tener según mi pequeña
experiencia, creo que este movimiento debe terminar para dar paso a lo que
circunstancialmente podría referirme como PDD, Pragmatic Driven Development
(Siguiendo con las directrices&hellip; yo también puedo ser muy molón con nombres que
quedan de lujo en mi currículum). Y es que estoy cansado de ver como la gente me
dice como tengo que enfocar mi proyecto, que prácticas debo seguir para hacerlo
&ldquo;bien&rdquo; y que directrices debo tomar para no estar lejos de la verdad absoluta.</p>

<p>La verdad absoluta no existe, o no debería existir. Cualquier discurso debería
tener una parte objetiva, basado en las buenas prácticas, pero también debería
tener una parte subjetiva, relativa a las circunstancias reales y propias del
proyecto. Pues parece ser que no se entiende. Parece ser que, y como si un
movimiento político desfasado y arcaico se tratara, el Ego ciega demasiado como
para poder entender tanta obviedad junta (será lo acostumbrados que nos tienen
a ser tratados como borregos).</p>

<p>Es por esto que personalmente me niego a escuchar más estupidez modernista sin
argumentos sólidos. Me niego a ser víctima de <em>hype</em> por parte de personas que no
tienen más formas de destacar que vender su pensamiento único como si de la
entrada al cielo de la sabiduría se tratara. Hemos llegado a un punto enfermizo.</p>

<p>Personalmente siempre exijo que la gente que me escucha tenga un pensamiento
propio, que trate mi opinión como otro punto de vista, aunque sea incorrecto,
distinto o distante, y que sirva como punto de soporte para dar aún más robustez
al argumento que pueda darle uno a un tema específico, dado un punto de partida
y un objetivo final.</p>

<p><strong>Que conste, no digo que las buenas prácticas no importen, no digo que tener
conocimientos sobre arquitectura no importe, no digo que aplicar una buena
metodología no importe&hellip;</strong> Creo que todas estas prácticas nacidas en grandes
mentes y probadas con grandes resultados son herramientas que nos hace mejores,
con más recursos y más capaces de trabajar problemas de forma satisfactoria.
Debo añadir que soy practicante de muchas de ellas en el punto en que las
necesito, y doy gracias a ello. Me hace mejor profesional. Lo que digo es que
somos desarrolladores, no gente estúpida sin capacidad de análisis. En el
momento que perdemos este análisis, perdemos completamente nuestro valor.</p>

<ul>
<li>Estoy haciendo este proyecto, ¿te gusta?</li>
<li>Espero que lo estés haciendo con Arquitectura Hexagonal&hellip;</li>
<li>Pues la verdad es que no la necesito&hellip;</li>
<li>¿Que no la necesitas? ¡Claro que la necesitas!</li>
<li>Pues no, en este caso no los necesito&hellip;</li>
<li>Lo estás haciendo mal.</li>
</ul>


<p>Se trata de pensar las cosas, y decidir por uno mismo qué necesitas en cada
momento, sin dejar que nadie, absolutamente nadie, te diga de forma categórica
como debes hacer su trabajo.</p>

<p>Espero de verdad que toda esta borrachera se acabe pronto, espero que en un
futuro empiece a haber comportamientos un poco más profesionales para trabajar
todos como un equipo o comunidad, que es lo que necesitamos, teniendo en cuenta
las cosas que verdaderamente importan: aprender y hacer buenos proyectos, no
importa el Framework, el lenguaje o la arquitectura.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
