<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: event | Because yes]]></title>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/categories/event/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-03T17:22:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marc Morera]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[yuhu@mmoreram.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Symfony Catalunya]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2016/03/03/symfony-catalunya/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-03T17:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2016/03/03/symfony-catalunya</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Imagine yourself in front of the Barcelona&rsquo;s beach in July. It sounds good,
right? Then, continue imagining yourself with a great Symfony environment, with
a very cold beer, amazing people and even better topics to talk about.</p>

<p>Isn&rsquo;t it the best plan ever?</p>

<p>Well, if you feel that you need it, then you should continue reading this
post&hellip;</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m very very pleased to tell you that this plan is going to happen this summer.
The Symfony Barcelona Association is working very hard on this first edition of
<a href="http://symfony.cat">Symfony Catalunya</a>, an international Symfony event placed
in our city. This event is 100% in english and is going to be very focused on
how Symfony can help us in our day by day and in our jobs.</p>

<p>What does it really mean? Let me explain you properly:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>0 hype</strong>. This doesn&rsquo;t mean that we will not talk about new concepts, like
React for example, but everything will be constructive and focused on your next
day work.</li>
<li><strong>New talks</strong>. Don&rsquo;t you feel that all events are populated with same talks year
after year? In this event you will find <strong>only</strong> new talks.</li>
<li><strong>Amazing speakers</strong>. Speakers are selected because their communication skills.
The speaker quality is as important as the talk quality, don&rsquo;t you think?</li>
<li>Community to Community. We will not make any money with that event. All earned
gains will be invested in you somehow.</li>
<li><strong>50 euros</strong> early bird ticket. <a href="http://symfony.cat/#tickets">Get yours</a> as soon
as possible and join us :)</li>
<li>Take some breath. 7 talks per day, one after another is never a good option.
With 4 talks per day you will be able to enjoy the city and the people.</li>
<li>Eat whatever you want, whenever you need. Your ticket doesn&rsquo;t include food,
but the venue is in front of great placed for having lunch and coffee.</li>
<li>Lighting talks. If you feel that you have something to show us, bring your 8
minutes speech.</li>
</ul>


<p>Of course, and because you&rsquo;re able to buy early bird tickets, we have published
4 of our 8 speakers in our website.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/matthiasnoback">Matthias Noback</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/acasademont">Albert Casademont</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/weaverryan">Ryan Weaver</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jmikola">Jeremy Mikola</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Companies</h2>

<p>Are you a company placed in some part of the world? Do you like Symfony? Then
this may interest you&hellip;</p>

<p>For only 300 euros you will be able to</p>

<ul>
<li>Put your logo everywhere. We will mention you in our media channels at least
once.</li>
<li>You will be able to add whatever you want in our Conference Attendee bag</li>
<li>You will get one free ticket for the conference</li>
<li>We will work very very hard to provide you an stand during the conference.</li>
<li>You will have the satisfaction to be helping the Symfony Environment, a very
important part if you are looking for Symfony developers</li>
</ul>


<p>We really appreciate companies sponsoring, and we strongly think that should
always be that cheaper.</p>

<h2>Communities</h2>

<p>Are you a PHP or Symfony community? Well, you can help us too by spreading the
word. In exchange of that, we will consider you part of our sponsoring group,
adding your logo in our list as well.</p>

<p>And is free!</p>

<p>How can you help us?
Well, for each new sponsor we have because of you, we will give you one free
ticket for the conference. You will be able to raffle this ticket among your
community.</p>

<h2>Join us</h2>

<p>Do you like that? Then&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://symfony.cat/#tickets">Join Symfony Catalunya now!</a></li>
</ul>


<p>To be aware of our news, follow our Twitter account
(<a href="http://twitter.com/symfonycat">@symfonycat</a>) and say hello :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Symfony UG, be our friend]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2015/09/14/symfony-ug-be-our-friend/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-14T10:57:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2015/09/14/symfony-ug-be-our-friend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Symfony Barcelona UG have been looking some sponsors for a while, and we have
had a great response from the community. We are so proud and happy about that.</p>

<p>As a User Group, we want to be a community group for all the community, so from
today, you can be our UG friend :)</p>

<p>If you are a Symfony UG around the world and you want to be part of it, very
easy. Just send an email to
<a href="symfonybarcelona@gmail.com">symfonybarcelona@gmail.com</a> or just a simple tweet
with <a href="http://twitter.com/symfony_bcn">@symfony_bcn</a>. We will add your logo in
our website and you will appear in our next event.</p>

<p>Then, we will be friends :)</p>

<p>Please, share this post on your social networks, and help us making a better
world with tons of tiny and cute cats :)</p>

<p>Have a nice week!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Symfony Barcelona Event, September 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2015/09/07/symfony-barcelona-event-september-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-07T21:38:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2015/09/07/symfony-barcelona-event-september-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is a pleasure for me to announce that next September 22nd we will have a
great event in Barcelona. I&rsquo;ve talked many times about this local organization,
but this time is pretty different. I&rsquo;ll explain you.</p>

<p>This year Barcelona hosts the
<a href="https://events.drupal.org/barcelona2015">DrupalCon Europe 2015</a>, and this is
super exciting. Many people from around the world will visit our great and
amazing streets and will attend to a great and big event, related with Drupal,
Symfony and other interesting topics, always, related to the Drupal world.</p>

<p>This is very interesting from the point of view of Symfony, because as you may
know, new version of drupal, Drupal8, is build using some Symfony components.
This is one of the examples I refer when I talk about sharing technologies
between PHP projects and when I talk about open source, community and other
related topics. We&rsquo;ve seen these synergies between other PHP projects and
Symfony as well with Laravel, eZ Publish, Magento and Joomla (and many more,
indeed)</p>

<p>So, this is a call to all the community coming to Barcelona next September 21st.
We will host Fabien Potencier, the creator of Symfony, and Lukas Kahwe Smith, an
amazing and super active PHP developer, member, for example, of the PHP-FIG
group.</p>

<p><a href="http://symfony-barcelona.es">http://symfony-barcelona.es</a></p>

<p>Isn&rsquo;t it interesting? Indeed, but this is not all!</p>

<p>We are planning to overcome our last assistance record, which is 140 attendees.
This time, we want to fill an auditorium of 600 seats and show you what really
is Barcelona, and how amazing can be :)</p>

<p>Our sponsors are ready<br/>
The community is ready<br/>
The organization is ready<br/>
Only one thing is missing here&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>You!</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://symfony-barcelona.es#register">Join us now for free!</a> and please share
this post to allow everyone to know about it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
