<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Zaragoza | Because yes]]></title>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/categories/zaragoza/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-07T21:57:53+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marc Morera]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[yuhu@mmoreram.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SymfonyWalk - c'est fini]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/11/25/symfony-walk-ends/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-25T12:13:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/11/25/symfony-walk-ends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>90Km walked in 3 days. And it&rsquo;s over.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been walking through amazing and gorgeous places during the last 3 days. I
had in mind going to Madrid, but I&rsquo;ve had two important problems.</p>

<ul>
<li>My feet. This is one of my problems. My feet. What&rsquo;s wrong with you?!</li>
<li>The next section was 42km, through the mountain and with any place where to
sleep. No hotels, no hostels, no nice people offering her house. It should not
be a problem, but the real problem has one single name. -6 degrees at night. I
cannot expose myself for sleeping on the street with that cold. All next
sections are like that, after 30-40km walking, nowhere to sleep.</li>
</ul>


<p>I feel disappointed with myself. I had so many expectations I could do that, but
I cannot put myself in danger 1 week before one of my most important moments on
my entirely professional life, to be a speaker in the SymfonyCon, in Madrid. My
fault.</p>

<p>But things happen. And what I wanted to demonstrate to myself is that I can do
that. Yes, sure, with more or less preparation&hellip; but I can do that. Because the
most difficult part of this things is trying them. And then, once tried, you can
fail. Lot of times. You will fail. Even if you don&rsquo;t expect that, you will fail.
But failing is just the beginning of success.</p>

<p>I will stay here, in the middle of nothing, since the SymfonyCon starts. Resting
and enjoying something different than Barcelona. The real world.</p>

<p>I want to thank all the people around the world that has encouraged me on this
event. I&rsquo;ll try again soon. Once and again till I achieve my goal. And once
achieved, I will go on with another goal. Because this is life, my friends, goal
after goal.</p>

<p>Looking forward to see you all in Madrid, this is going to be a great great
event.</p>

<p>PD: Ryan, my friend, I will also take a plane XD</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SymfonyWalk - Sleeping bag]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/symfonywalk-sleeping-bag/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T18:51:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/symfonywalk-sleeping-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I expected it would be much easier. Indeed, it should be easier, but once again,
the effort on something is just the beginning of something simply bigger called
&ldquo;The plan&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The problem is that I thought if would be much simple to sleep from Zaragoza to
Madrid.</p>

<p>It is not. Damn!</p>

<p>So this is why I will have to sleep in a sleeping bag 9 days. I don&rsquo;t exactly
know where will I be able to clean myself, or to eat something, or sleep. In
fact this is what OpenSource is. All OpenSource developers are Walkers in a
world without hostels, but nice people.</p>

<p>I expect I will find some contributors around the adventure.</p>

<ul>
<li>Food Pull Requests?</li>
<li>Bed Pull Requests?</li>
<li>Water Pull Requests?</li>
</ul>


<p>7 days to go. I am ready. Am I?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Symfony Walk, the Conference section]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/10/15/symfony-walk-symfony-con-section/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T11:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/10/15/symfony-walk-symfony-con-section</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The day is getting closer. I am really exited about the idea of the <a href="http://mmoreram.com/blog/2014/08/07/symfony-walk-zaragoza-madrid/">Symfony Walk</a>.</p>

<p>As you may know, the walk will consists in 12 days (10 walking, 2 resting, 1
resting day added as announced for my health), from Zaragoza to Madrid, so today
I want to announce formally the last section of the Walk, dedicated to the
people in the conference and to the entirely Symfony Community.</p>

<p>I want to open source the last part of my experience. I&rsquo;d like everyone excited
with the idea to walk beside me for the last 38km.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s the plan:</p>

<p><img src="/images/zaragoza-madrid-last-section.png" title="[Zaragoza Madrid Last Section [Zaragoza Madrid Las Section]]" ></p>

<ul>
<li>From &ndash; 26 Nov at 10.00 &ndash; <a href="https://www.google.es/maps/place/Hotel+Azuqueca/@40.574603,-3.260397,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0xd424d58faf1da8d:0x4d83f8902082a9e8?hl=ca">Hotel Azuqueca, Azuqueca de Henares, Guadalajara</a></li>
<li>To &ndash; 26 November at 19.00 &ndash; <a href="https://www.google.es/maps/search/hotel+auditorium/@40.448706,-3.5586655,17z/data=!3m2!4b1!5s0xd4230487e9da459:0xa7e56b7dca610362?hl=ca">Hotel Auditorium, Madrid</a></li>
<li>Good shoes, important!</li>
<li>We could talk about symfony stuff and some interesting topics.</li>
</ul>


<p>Excited about that? Good! Once in Madrid, a cold beer will be our best friend&hellip;
ever!</p>

<p>Let me know if you want to join us through the
<a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/symfony-walk-symfonycon-section-tickets-13728858385">Eventbrite event</a>,
so we can organize based on the total number of people. You can also contact me
through my email, <a href="&#109;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x79;&#x75;&#x68;&#117;&#x40;&#x6d;&#109;&#x6f;&#114;&#101;&#x72;&#97;&#109;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#109;&#46;">&#121;&#x75;&#x68;&#x75;&#x40;&#x6d;&#x6d;&#111;&#114;&#x65;&#x72;&#97;&#109;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;&#46;</a></p>

<p>Looking forward to meet you there, it is going to be amazing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One section, one component]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/08/12/one-section-one-component/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-12T11:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/08/12/one-section-one-component</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/08/07/symfony-walk-zaragoza-madrid/">Symfony Walk</a></p>

<p><img class="[class names]" src="/images/zaragoza-madrid.png" title="[Zaragoza Madrid [Zaragoza Madrid]]" ></p>

<p>Symfony Walk will contain a total of 10 sections, and each one will have the
name of one Symfony Component. One of the sections will be named <em>Doctrine</em> (yes,
our big friend Doctrine) and last Component will be named like the project I am
so proud to work in, <a href="http://elcodi.io">Elcodi</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/routing/index.html">Routing</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/security/index.html">Security</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/console/index.html">Console</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/finder.html">Finder</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://doctrine-orm.readthedocs.org/en/latest/">Doctrine</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/event_dispatcher/index.html">EventDispatcher</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/http_kernel/index.html">HttpKernel</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/form/index.html">Form</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/dependency_injection/index.html">DependencyInjection</a> Section</li>
<li><a href="http://elcodi.io">Elcodi</a> Section</li>
</ul>


<p>Each day, after walking around 35 Km in about 6 hours, I will post a small
introduction about the component that names the current section. I&rsquo;ll talk also
about some scenarios that this component can be useful.</p>

<p>Happy Symfony Walk.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Symfony Walk: Zaragoza - Madrid]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/08/07/symfony-walk-zaragoza-madrid/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-07T13:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/08/07/symfony-walk-zaragoza-madrid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The 2014 Madrid SymfonyCon is closer every day, and I have to admit that
I admire this community. A community that has been able to feed the php world
with valuable projects and better people.</p>

<p>I admire the synergies that are created in different repositories that make
Symfony one of the best options when developing any
web project, and the entire ecosystem that has been created around, an ecosystem
very healthy and social.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;ll pay my own tribute the coming months.</p>

<h3>Symfony Walk 2014</h3>

<p>The goal is to walk a path to SymfonyCon Madrid with no more tools than a
backpack and good music. The principle of such route will be Zaragoza, so the
road will be a total of about 360 kilometers.</p>

<p>I will divide the challenge in 10 days plus one resting day. During the next few
days I will also define the final route and all resting points, where I will
spend nights.</p>

<p>My reasons are none other than a mixture of personal challenge of something I&rsquo;ve
wanted to do for a long time and my gratitude to this community for all
help I&rsquo;ve received indirectly.</p>

<p>As you know I work on a project called [Elcodi] (<a href="http://elcodi.io">http://elcodi.io</a>). we have
very clear which is our philosophy and the details that we care until the
last sighs of the project, and we know it&rsquo;s not easy.</p>

<p>We have overcome challenges as an <em>open source</em> project , we are overcoming
challenges as an <em>open source</em> project, and hopefully over the next few years we
should overcome greater challenges as <em>open source</em> project .</p>

<p>Well, I think the act of walking for 70 hours in 10 days is a good
representation of what needs hard work, effort and time, but finally, in the
bottom of the road, a great reward awaits your arrival.</p>

<p>In my case, the conference .</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll post more details about my little adventure soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
