<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ecommerce | Because yes]]></title>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/categories/ecommerce/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-12T12:16:31+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marc Morera]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[yuhu@mmoreram.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elcodi wants you]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/07/21/elcodi-wants-you/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-21T21:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/07/21/elcodi-wants-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Right. Elcodi wants you.</p>

<p><a href="http://elcodi.io">Elcodi Project</a></p>

<p>And Elcodi wants you because you are ambitious, a fighter, a ninja developer
eager to learn and to teach.</p>

<p>Elcodi wants you because you are a follower of good practices and have a sound
software craftsmanship mindset, because you are a perfectionist, because your
inspiring work is a way of life.</p>

<p>Elcodi wants you because you firmly believe that an open-source environment is a
trigger that can detonate personal and professional achievements.</p>

<p>We believe we are doing a good job. We are not alone in believing it, many
others do. This is why we have decided take it to the next level and start to
evolve, growing the team and our vision.</p>

<p>We really aim to make things the right way by unfolding the power of
collaborative software development and this is why we need your voice, your
ideas, your enthusiasm and, of course, we need your hands. Skillful, experienced
and visionary artisan hands.</p>

<p>If you share our vision and want to collaborate with a truly inspiring project,
contact me at <code>yuhu@mmoreram.com</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elcodi, a new Symfony adventure]]></title>
    <link href="http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/04/29/elcodi-a-new-symfony-adventure/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T16:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mmoreram.github.io/blog/2014/04/29/elcodi-a-new-symfony-adventure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some changes are about to come. And it seems that they are good
changes. I haven’t written in my blog for a few weeks, and the truth is
I feel bad about it. I like to write about the things that happen to me at
the company; about the problems we find and the solutions I come up
with. The thing is that, for some months now, I’ve been really focused
on the project that we are launching to the world today. Initially, it is
a project by developers for developers, focused on meeting the actual
needs of developers who design and program e-commerce.</p>

<p>It is true that we have plenty of platforms and options to develop e-
commerce around the world. I could name a few, and probably they all
have outstanding metrics and KPIs.</p>

<p>The problem with these platforms is that they are entirely B2B, so
they only make sense when the end user just needs to have a good
management, installation and configuration interface; and when
technical departments want to develop, both horizontally (new features
for things already in use, or just customization) and vertically (new
features), these B2B platforms fall short, and so the company must
either pay a lot of money in refactoring, or the existing code must be
touched, contaminating it and putting its integrity at risk.</p>

<p>These platforms are usually not tested, and so each line added is
potentially harmful for the whole system. Then, each development
on these platforms usually results in collateral problems in the user
experience itself.</p>

<p>As I see it, this is unacceptable in our times.
We propose a platform conceived for developers, thought of and deeply
reflected on. This does not mean that the code is right from the very
start; our declaration of intent is simply to take this project to a certain
point where companies can trust in the project in order to build their
own.</p>

<p>We present you <a href="http://elcodi.io">Elcodi</a>.</p>

<p>We are just beginning to emerge with an approach divided into phases.
Our roadmap is very clear to us, and so in the next few months we
will develop the main features at a core level, as well as the necessary
robustness in order to deal with any outsourcers who like the project in
its initial stage and wish to join us in this journey, aimed at improving
the lifestyle of developers.</p>

<p>The platform is based on Symfony2 and, following the philosophy
defined by its own framework, we have focused most of the
architecture by using a strong layer of events, fully uncoupling most
behaviours and components.</p>

<p>If you are a Symfony programmer, I suggest that you check it out. You
will see errors, a thousand things left to develop and to improve; but,
like with all projects, our greatest ambition is its own construction;
therefore, it’s a matter of months, energy and development.
Another of our objectives is building a good documentation.</p>

<p>Essentially, we have three documentation lines in mind. Firstly, we
want to communicate our philosophy to other people; the direction
the project will undoubtedly take, regardless of its implementation
in a given moment. It is important to define this from the beginning,
because to a great extent it links us to our target audience.
Documentation is a slow process, which is also subject to collaboration,
and at first it will be in English only.</p>

<p>Finally, I should say that elcodi.com is a rapidly expanding company.
We have good growth projections, and so we are certain that what we
are starting today with such enthusiasm will not cease to grow.
We want it to be useful; we want our proposal to be seen by everybody,
to get your most constructive criticism, since only in this way we can
really make an interesting project for us all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
